<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>XSpec</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on XSpec</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://xspec.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Release XSpec v3.2.2</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_322_release/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_322_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v3.2.2 XSpec 3.2 enhances its HTML reports with coverage statistics and a choice of color themes. These are the highlights of XSpec v3.2:
Common to Languages Under Test Test reports use black text on white background by default, improving accessibility. Themes 'whiteblack' (white on black) and 'classic' (earlier green/pink design) are also available. You can select a non-default theme using the xspec.html.report.theme Ant property or, in the command line interface, the XSPEC_HTML_REPORT_THEME environment variable.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v3.1.2</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_312_release/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_312_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v3.1.2 XSpec 3.1.2 fixes bugs in the coverage status shown in XSLT code coverage reports. This release also updates dependencies. These are the highlights of XSpec v3.1:
Common to Languages Under Test XSpec is tested with Saxon 12.5, except that the detailed contents of XSLT code coverage reports are tested with Saxon 12.4. The XSpec schemas enforce the boolean values for the x:expand-text attribute and provide a Schematron Quick Fix for expand-text attributes on non-XSpec elements.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v3.0.3</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_303_release/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_303_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v3.0.3 Release v3.0.3 upgrades its connections with related software. Support for testing Schematron schemas now uses SchXslt as the built-in Schematron implementation. XSLT code coverage is compatible with Saxon 12.4 or later. These are the highlights of XSpec v3.0:
Common to Languages Under Test XSpec is tested with Saxon 12, 11, and 10, while use of Saxon versions earlier than 12.4 is not recommended. XSpec no longer supports Saxon 9.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v2.3.2</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_232_release/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_232_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v2.3.2 Release v2.3 fixes bugs, updates dependencies, and includes some refactoring. These are the highlights for XSpec v2.3.2:
Common to Languages Under Test Saxon 9.8 is no longer supported. XSpec is now tested with Saxon 12, 11, 10, and 9.9, while Saxon 9.9 is deprecated. Command line support fixes a bug that produced the wrong XSPEC_HOME value. Schematron Ant performs some preprocessing in parallel, improving performance.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v2.2.4</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_224_release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_224_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v2.2.4 Release v2.2.4 introduces new features and enhancements, fixes bugs, and improves the test suite and the documentation. These are the highlights for XSpec v2.2.4:
Common to Languages Under Test Pending or unfocused variable declarations are handled more gracefully. Large results are no longer saved in separate XML files by default. This will be the last version to support Saxon 9.8. XSLT Multiple test scenarios can be run in parallel by setting @threads on x:description or x:scenario.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v2.1.4</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_214_release/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_214_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v2.1.4 Release v2.1.4 introduces new features and enhancements, fixes bugs, and improves the test suite and the documentation. These are the highlights for XSpec v2.1.4:
Common to Languages Under Test You can mark assertions as pending by setting @pending on x:expect, as an alternative to using the x:pending element. /x:description/@measure-time measures elapsed run times of scenarios. (Requires Saxon-PE or EE.) XSLT Different scenarios can use different global parameters (//x:scenario/x:param).</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v2.0.7</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_207_release/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_207_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v2.0.7 Release v2.0.7 introduces new features and enhancements, fixes bugs, and improves the test suite and the documentation. These are the highlights for XSpec v2.0.7:
Common to Languages Under Test x:helper lets you integrate your own test helpers @as can be set in x:context and x:expect XSLT You can test XSLT packages and static parameters (experimental) Schematron Compatible with SchXslt (not thoroughly tested) You can write advanced expressions in @location (e.</description></item><item><title>Release XSpec v1.6.0</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_160_release/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/posts/xspec_160_release/</guid><description>Release XSpec v1.6.0 Release v1.6.0 introduces new features and enhancements, fixes bugs, and improves the test suite and the documentation. These are the highlights for XSpec v1.6.0:
Text Value Templates (expand-text) Code Coverage now works on Saxon-HE Compatible with Saxon 10.0 Note: Code Coverage does not work on Saxon 10 (#852) Compatible with Oxygen 22.0 This will be the last version to support Saxon 9.7 Many thanks to the many XSpec contributors who made this release possible.</description></item><item><title>About XSpec</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/about/</guid><description>XSpec is a unit test and behaviour-driven development (BDD) framework for XSLT, XQuery, and Schematron. It is based on the Spec framework of RSpec, which is a BDD framework for Ruby.
XSpec consists of a syntax for describing the behaviour of XSLT, XQuery, or Schematron code, and some code that enables you to test the code against those descriptions.
To get started, check out the installation instructions for macOS/Linux and Windows and how to write your first XSpec test.</description></item><item><title>Contribute</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/contribute/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/contribute/</guid><description>If you wish to contribute to XSpec, please read the contributing guidelines and then raise or pick up an issue and send us your pull requests. Please document any issue with examples of your XSpec code.</description></item><item><title>Documentation</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/documentation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/documentation/</guid><description>The latest XSpec documentation is available as a wiki on GitHub.</description></item><item><title>Get Help</title><link>https://xspec.github.io/help/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://xspec.github.io/help/</guid><description>Check out the XSpec documentation in the wiki. If you have any question that is not answered in the wiki, feel free to raise an issue.</description></item></channel></rss>